Edmund Clarence Stedman Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Edmund Clarence Stedman Collection
1860-1915
YCAL MSS 1008
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.67
(5 boxes)
Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded in the finding aid when known. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical/Historical note
Edmund Clarence Stedman was born in Hartford, Connecticut, on October 8, 1833, the son of Edmund Burke Stedman, a lumber merchant, and Elizabeth Clementine (Dodge) Stedman, a poet. He attended Yale College for two years, and then began a career as a journalist in New York. During the Civil War he served as Washington Correspondent for the New York World, but after the war resigned this position and bought a seat on the New York Stock Exchange. Concurrent with his career in banking, Stedman devoted himself to poetry and literary criticism. Major editorial works include Victorian Poets (1875) and Poets of America (1885).
Stedman married Laura Hyde Woodworth in 1853. They had two sons, Frederick and Arthur. His granddaughter Laura Woodworth Stedman served as Stedman's secretary in the last years of his life, and later as his literary executor. Stedman died of a heart attack on January 18, 1908.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the professional literary work and personal life of the writer Edmund Clarence Stedman. It includes incoming and outgoing correspondence with fellow writers and editors, with publishers, and with friends and family. A small number of autograph manuscripts of his writings are present. The collection also contains papers of and correspondence among Stedman's extended family, including his mother Elizabeth Kinney; his wife Laura Hyde Woodworth Stedman; his son Frederick Stedman; Frederick's wife Ellen Douglas Stedman; and the Douglas family. Correspondence and papers of Frederick Stedman's daughter, Laura Woodworth Stedman Gould Dees, who served as literary executor for her grandfather, chiefly concern E.C. Stedman's work and legacy.
Arrangement
Arranged in the order in which the library maintained the collection from its inception in the 1940s. Items and groups of items were numbered by the library between the 1940s-1962; the collection remains in this numerical order.
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Authors -- United States -- 19th century; Douglas, George, 1829-1899; Kinney, Elizabeth C. (Elizabeth Clementine), 1810-1889; Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908; Stedman, Ellen Montague Douglas, 1855-1931; Stedman, Frederick Stuart, 1856-1906; Stedman, Laura, 1881-1939; Stedman, Laura Hyde Woodworth, 1833-1905
- Autograph letter, signed, to William E. Dodge: [New York City?]. 2 pages., 1875 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased on the Plain Fund, 1941
- Autograph letter, signed, to George Alfred Townsend: Bronxville. 1 page., 1896 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Charles D. Hamill: New York City. 3 pages., 1891 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Gift of Mrs. Hamill, 1943
- Autograph letter, signed, to John James Piatt: Newark, N.J. 4 pages., 1871 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Gift of Mr. Knollenberg, 1946
- Autograph letter, signed, to John Swinton: New York City. With additional autograph note written on back of addressed envelope., 1881 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Autograph note, signed, to [William Henry] Rideing: Kelp Rock, [Newcastle, New Hampshire]. 2 pages., 1887 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Purchased on the Plain Fund, 1940
- Autograph letter, signed, to Franklin Benjamin Sanborn: New York City. 4 pages., 1884 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Purchased on the Southworth Fund, 1940
- Autograph letter, signed, to an unidentified correspondent: New York City. 3 pages., 1876 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Autograph letter, signed, to Benjamin H. Ticknor: New York City. 2 pages., 1883 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Gift of Owen F. Aldis, 1911.
- Manuscript note, signed, expressing his opinion of Ellen Mackay Hutchingson's Songs and Lyrics., 1881 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Gift of Owen F. Aldis, 1911
- 2 Autograph letters, signed, to William Whitman Bailey: New York City and Bronxville., 1889 August 31, 1897 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Purchased on the Plain Fund, 1942
- Autograph letter, signed, to [Willam Henry] Bishop: New York City. 4 pages., 1882 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Acquired through exchange, 1943
- Autograph letter, signed, to William Whitman Bailey: New York City. 2 pages., 1896 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Purchased on the Class of 1884 Fund, 1946
- 51 Autograph letters and notes, signed (four on postal-cards), to his granddaughter Laura Woodworth Stedman: various places, 1888-1907; 3 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
  Gift of the estate of Laura Stedman Dees, 1939
- 5 undated autograph notes, signed, to Laura Woodworth Stedman (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Manuscript poem, "To my Youthful Mother, on her seventy-fifth Birthday." Signed, with addressed envelope., 1885 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Autograph letter, signed, to his mother, Elizabeth Clementine (Dodge) Stedman Kinney: New York., 1887 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- 36 Autograph letters and notes, signed (on postal cards), to his daughter-in-law Ellen (Douglas) Stedman: various places., 1878-1907 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Typewritten letter signed to Ellen (Douglas) Stedman: New York City., 1907 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- 3 Autograph notes, signed, to Ellen (Douglas) Stedman, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Autograph note, signed, to Ellen Montague Douglas: New York City., 1878 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Autograph telegram to his son, Frederick Stuart Stedman: New York City., 1905 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- 6 Autograph notes, signed, to George Douglas: New York City., 1888-1892 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Autograph letter, signed, to [Amelia M.] Daggett (afterwards Mrs. G. St. J. Sheffield): New York City. 2 pages with envelope., 1876 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Gift of the estate of Mrs. George St. John Sheffield, 1937
- Autograph note, signed, to Henry C. Bowen: New York City. 2 pages., 1886 April 24 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Purchased from Heise on the Plain Fund, 1940
- Manuscript letter, signed (by a secretary?), to Dr. Frederic Peterson: New York, 1884 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Gift of Frederick J. Shepard, 1930
- Original manuscripts of poems, 1871, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Scope and Contents
  [Autumn at Gloucester Bay] (with two typed copies)
  The Escape (with typed copy)
  Idyll I: Dirge for Adonis
  Immortal Father, Soverign God
  Midsummer Bride of Death
  Over the Summer Sea
  Poetic Loquition: A vague Memento of a Troubled Mood [dated July 4, 1871]
  Sister, Sister, Let No Hands
  Suggestion for a Poem--Was It For This So Long
  Gift of the Estate of Laura Stedman Dees, 1939
- Miscellaneous manuscript notes of various kinds. 3 pages., undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Eggleston, George Cary (1839-1911). 2 Autograph letters, signed, to Frederick S. Stedman: New York City, 1881 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Garland, Hamlin. Autograph note, signed., 1894 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Linton, William James, Autograph note, signed, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Dees, Laura Stedman Gould. Correspondence concerning her uncle, Malcolm Douglas, 4 (Box 1, Folder 34-37)
- Douglas, George (1829-1899), 1888-1893
  - Miscellaneous manuscript poems, undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 38-40)
  - 3 Autograph letters, signed, to his daughter Ellen (Douglas) Stedman, 1860-1880 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Invitation to the wedding of Ellen Montague Douglas to Frederick Stuart Stedman, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - 10 Autograph letters, signed,to E.C. Stedman, 1888-1893 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - 4 Autograph letters, signed, to his granddaughter Laura Stedman, 1886-1888 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - 3 Autograph letters, signed, to his sister Mrs. Horace Green, 1897-1898 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Kinney, Elizabeth Clementine (Dodge) Stedman (1810-1889)
  - Manuscript poems, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Printed copy of her poem, "Desires", undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - 6 Autograph letters, signed, to Ellen (Douglas) Stedman, 1880-1888 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - 3 Autograph letters, signed, to Laura Woodworth Stedman, 1885-1887 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Autograph letter, signed,to M. Vattamere, with 2 poems, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Stedman, Ellen Montague (Douglas) (1855-1931)
  - 31 Autograph letters, signed, to her daughter Laura W. (Stedman) Gould, 1890-1927 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Marriage certificate of Ellen Montague Douglas and Frederick Stuart Stedman, enclosed in bound volume titled "Our Marriage Vow," containing marriage service and newspaper accounts of the wedding., 1880 March 31 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Miscellaneous letters to her from family and friends, together with miscellaneous papers connected with the Douglas family, undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 53-55)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to her father, George Douglas: Palenville, New York., 1883 August 21 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - 3 Autograph letters, signed to her father-in-law, Edmund Clarence Stedman: New Castle, New Hampshire, and New York City, 1884-1890 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - 14 Autograph letters, signed, to her mother-in-law, Laura Hyde (Woodworth) Stedman: various places, 1880-1884 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Stedman, Frederick Stuart (1856-1906)
  - 13 Autograph letters, signed, to his father and mother: New York City and Pittsburgh, 1878-1905 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Telegram to Thomas Bailey Aldrich, 1881 February 18 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Stedman, Laura Hyde (Woodworth) (1834-1905)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to her granddaughter Laura Woodworth Stedman (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Alice of Monmouth: an Idyl of the Great War With Other Poems: original autograph manuscript. 185 pages. [published New York, 1864], undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
- English Poetry of the Period (For the North American Review): original manuscript review, signed by the author. 44 pages., undated; Bound in three-quarter white parchment wtih grey cloth covers. (Box 3, Folder 63)
- Linton's "Love-Lore": Original manuscript review written for "The Critic." 14 pages., 1887; Bound in three-quarter white parchment, with grey board covers. (Box 4, Folder 64)
- Letters removed from books by Stedman in the Aldis collection
  - Mimeographed letter, signed, with manuscript address and additions, and autograph note, signed, to the Reverend William R. Alger: New York City., 1886 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to the Reverend W. R. Alger: New York City. 2 pages., 1889 February 25 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Mimeographed letter, with manuscript heading, additions, and signature, to Mrs. Anne Charlotte Lynch Botta: New York City, 1886 January 18 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Autograph note, signed, to John Swinton: New York City, 1881 December 7 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - 2 Autograph letters, signed, to the editors of "Poet-Lore" [Charlotte Porter and Helen Archibald Clarke]: New York City, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Autograph note, signed, to the editor of the "Independent" [Henry Chandler Bowen]: New Castle, New Hampshire, 1886 October 16 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Autograph note signed with initials to Henry Chandler Bowen, [New York City], circa 1887 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Autograph note, signed, to H. C. Bowen: New York City, 1889 January 23 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - "Ad Vigilem": typewritten poem on Whittier's eightieth birthday, undated (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Autograph note, signed, to [James Ripley] Osgood: New York City, 1869 May 8 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Quotation and autograph, undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Aldrich, Thomas Bailey. Autograph letter, signed, to [James Ripley] Osgood, 1873 August 8 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to Benjamin H. Ticknor: New York City, 1885 October 23 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Manuscript copy, signed, of three stanzas from his poem, "Holyoke Valley", with inscription to Colonel William S. Shurtleff: New York City, 1878 February 26 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Letter to William E. Dodge: Brownsville, 1897 October 30 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - "The Singer", manuscript copy of poem, signed by the author, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to Ella Farman Pratt: New York City, 1887 March 23 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - MS note about his poem "The Star-Bearer", after 1900 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    Note on verso from [Patrick Kevin Foley] to Mrs. Powers, undated.
  - Foley, Patrick Kevin. Manuscript note about the printing of Stedman's poem, "The Star Bearer", 1904 February 27 (Box 4, Folder 79)
- Henderson, D. M., autograph letter to Stedman. Baltimore., 1888 September 20 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  Accompanied by printed adverstisement for Henderson's Poems, Scottish and American.
  Removed from Henderson's Poems, Scottish and American. Gift of the estate of Laura Stedman Dees.
- Sturgis, Russell (1836-1909). Autograph letter, signed, to Stedman. New York., 1892 December 19 (Box 4, Folder 81)
- Manuscripts removed from his An American Anthology (1900)
  Gift of Laura Stedman Dees
  - [Proctor, Edna Dean]. Letter, typescript carbon, to Miss Stedman, 1914 April 18 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    General note
    Annotated: "Other copy with her papers"
  - Gay, H. Nelson. Autograph letter, signed, to E.C. Stedman. Rome., 1907 January 2 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    Accompanied by ephemera regarding the Shelley Memorial
  - [Gilder, Richard Watson?]. Autograph postcard, signed., 1907 February 3 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - De Kay, Charles. Autograph letter, signed., 1882 October 18 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Invitation to E.C. Stedman to join New York Authors Club, 1882 November 1 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Copy of autograph letter, signed, from E.C. Stedman to Kate Field, 1892 April 23 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Copy of autograph letter, signed, from E.C. Stedman to Mr. D.G. Groly, 1888 December 24 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Johnson, Robert Underwood. Manuscript notes regarding errata in the Life and Letters of Edmund Clarence Stedman, annotated by Laura Stedman, undated (Box 4, Folder 82)
- Letters to E.C. Stedman removed from books by Stedman acquired from Morse
  Frear gift, 1942
  - Andrews, W. S., Autograph letter, signed, to E.C. Stedman, 1873 January 29 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Bromley, Isaac H., autograph letter, signed, 1877 March 12 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Brooks, Noah, autograph letter, signed, 1880 January 2 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Elderkin, John, autograph letter, signed, 1891 October 8 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Florence, W. J., autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Gill, William Fearing, autograph letter, signed, 1883 March 24 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Gray, Edward, autograph letter, signed, 1888 June 23 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Hager, J. Henry, autograph letter, signed, 1886 December 22 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Hay, John, autograph letter, signed, 1866 June 9 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Knox, Thomas Wallace, autograph letter, signed, 1885 January 6 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Matthews, Brander, autograph letter, signed, 1881 November 1 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Olcott, Henry S., autograph letter, signed, 1874 May 30 (Box 4, Folder 83)
- Sutro, Florence Clinton, autograph letter, signed, to E.C. Stedman, 1906 January 22 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  Removed from Milestones on Life's Pathway (1905). Sent to Donald Gallup, 1953
- 12 autograph letters and notes to William C. Gillman. Bronxville and New York City, 1905-1907 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  Source unknown
  Accompanied by drafts of two replies
- 2 autograph letters, signed, to William J. Linton. New York City and Summit, New Jersey, 1877 January 21, 1878 April 28 (Box 4, Folder 86)
- Autograph note, signed, to Thomas Allibone Janvier. New York City, [1903 July] (Box 4, Folder 87)
- "Westminster Abbey," autograph manuscript, signed with initials. 12 pages, undated (Box 4, Folder 88)
  Gift of Morgan Brainard, 1949
  Accompanied by Henkels, Stan. V., Catalogue No. 1055, The Valuable Literary Correspondence of the Late Poet, Edmund Clarence Stedman, Esq. of New York City. 1912
- Autograph letter, signed, to Charles L. Webster and Company. New Castle, New Hampshire. 4 pages, 1890 October 8 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  From Watkins autograph collection
- Autograph note, signed, on a calling card. Bronxville, N.Y., undated (Box 4, Folder 90)
  Gift of Donald C. Bakewell, 1940
- Autograph letter, signed, to Albert S. Cook. New York. 2 pages, 1895 November 27 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  Gift of Morris A. Neufeld, 1947 (through Norman Holmes Pearson)
- "Bohemia" quotation, autograph manuscript. Four and a half lines written out for Miss Alma Noble and signed, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  Gift of Mrs. Camp Buck, 1935
- Autographed place card. New York City., 1877 May 8 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  With the signatures apparently of other guests at a dinner
- Young, James Carleton. Autograph letter, signed, to E.C. Stedman. Minneapolis, Minnesota, 1906 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  Concerns Arthur Upson
- Autograph letter to Mr. Lincoln, [1893?] (Box 4, Folder 95)
- Autograph letter, signed, to Richard Hovey. New York City., 1896 July 20 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  Purchased with correspondence addressed to W. H. Wright with Matthiessen funds.
- Tinker, Chauncey Brewster. "Edmund Clarence Stedman. An Address Delivered Before the American Academy, November 9, 1938." Typescript (original), with manuscript corrections. 13 [i.e. 14] numbered leaves. (Box 4, Folder 97)
- Autograph note, signed, to Richard Watson Gilder, written on version of a printed poem (with manuscript corrections) by John Herbert Boner, [1889 October?] (Box 4, Folder 98)
  Removed from Za copy of H. W. Mabie's Books and Culture, purchased on the Alvord fund.
- Letters given by James T. Babb
  Gift of James T. Babb, 1962
  - 9 autograph letters, signed, to Stone and Kimball, 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    Includes notes to the printer concerning an edition of Poe's works.
  - Autograph letter, signed, to Lawrence. New York City., 1891 March 2 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Letter, signed, to Mr. Conway, chairman of the Nominating Committee of the American Author's Guild. New York City. 3 pages, 1896 October 12 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    The greater part of the letter is in the hand of an amanuensis.
  - Autograph letter, signed, to Henry C. Bowen. New York City. 3 pages, 1883 December 27 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Autograph letter to Mrs. [Octavius Brooks] Frotheringham. Coleman House. 2 pages., 1877 March 12 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to Jeanette L. Gilder. New York City. 1 page., 1885 May 5 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to George C. Holt. New York City. 1 page., 1901 February 13 (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - Autograph letter to Houghton, Mifflin, and Company. 1 page., [1895 August] (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Autograph letter to Mrs. Pratt. New Castle, New Hampshire. 4 pages., 1886 August 5 (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to Charles W. Stoddard. New York City. 2 pages., 1878 August 6 (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to "Mrs. Micawber" [Mrs. Richard Henry Stoddard]. Center Harbor. 4 pages., 1864 July 24 (Box 4, Folder 109)
    Signed: "D. Copperfield"
  - 3 autograph letters, signed, to Charles B. Todd. New York and Bronxville. 7 pages., 1887-1906 (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Townsend. New York City. 2 pages., 1884 January 13 (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Warren. New Castle, New Hampshire. 6 pages., 1886 August 2 (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Worthington. New York City. 2 pages., 1895 January 9 (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - 2 Autograph letters, signed, and 1 letter, signed, to Colonel David B. Sickels. New York and Bronxville. 7 pages., 1896-1898 (Box 4, Folder 114)
- Calling card of Ernest J. Dennen, inscribed: "Even though your wants are none, would you be good enough to accept this book of mine?", undated (Box 4, Folder 115)
- "Mr. Stedman's pen holder (he used an Esterbrook Judge's Quill), his knife, and his quill box." [M. Fuller], undated (Box 5)
  One pen (American Pencil Company, New York), with metal quill; two new quills inside a round wooden box; and one folding knife in a leather case.
  Accompanied by note, inside the round box: "Mr. Stedman left me this (with stamps in it), his pen, and paste pot, paper cutter, & [tiny?] tray behind for me."
  Custodial History
  Bequeathed to his friend and one-time secretary, Margaret Fuller.
  Gift of Charlotte Fuller Eastman, 1961